Guide to the Richard Goldstone Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Richard Henry Goldstone Papers
1915-1976
YCAL MSS 1106
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.54
(4 boxes)
The papers document Richard Goldstone's process of writing Thornton Wilder's biography, Thornton Wilder: An Intimate Portrait. The collection includes photocopied and original correspondence between Goldstone and Wilder, Goldstone's research notes on Wilder's career and family life, and book reviews and correspondence in response to Goldstone's biography. The collection also contains correspondence between Wilder and friends and family, as well as Goldstone's correspondence with Isabel Wilder and others associated wtih Wilder during the course of his writing the biography.
Goldstone, Richard Henry
Scope and Contents
The papers document Richard Goldstone's process of writing Thornton Wilder's biography, Thornton Wilder: An Intimate Portrait which was published in 1975. The collection includes photocopied and original correspondence between Goldstone and Wilder, Goldstone's research notes on Wilder's career and family life, and book reviews and correspondence in response to Goldstone's biography. The collection also contains correspondence between Wilder and friends and family, as well as Goldstone's correspondence with Isabel Wilder and others associated wtih Wilder during the course of his writing the biography.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Collections are processed to a variety of levels, depending on the work necessary to make them usable, their perceived research value, the availability of staff, competing priorities, and whether or not further accruals are expected. The library attempts to provide a basic level of preservation and access for all collections, and does more extensive processing of higher priority collections as time and resources permit.
This collection received a basic level of processing, including rehousing and minimal organization. Various acquisitions associated with the collection have not been merged and organized as a whole. Each acquisition is described separately in the contents list below, identified by a unique call number and titled according to month and year of acquisition.
Information included in the Description of Papers note and Collection Contents section is drawn from information supplied with the collection and from an initial survey of the contents. Folder titles appearing in the contents list below are often based on those provided by the creator or previous custodian. Titles have not been verified against the contents of the folders in all cases. Otherwise, folder titles are supplied by staff during initial processing.
This finding aid may be updated periodically to account for new acquisitions to the collection and/or revisions in arrangement and description.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Henry Goldstone, professor of English at the College of the City of New York. Goldstone published a biography of Thornton Wilder entitled Thornton Wilder: An Intimate Portrait (New York: Saturday Review Press) in 1975.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: 1976 Acquisition and 1991 Acquisition.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Richard Goldstone in 1976 and 1991.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Goldstone, Richard Henry; Goldstone, Richard Henry ( Thornton Wilder); Wilder, Isabel, 1900-1995; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Goldstone, Richard Henry
- 1976 Acquisition, 1915-1976; Series I; 1.33 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The 1976 Acquisition includes Goldstone's research on Wilder, correspondence, clippings, and programs.
  Arrangement
  The notecards and other groupings of materials are arranged in the order in which they were recieved by the library. The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Research notecards, circa 1973 (Box 1)
    Notecards Goldstone used in the course of his research on Thornton Wilder's life.
  - New York Times Book Review clipping, 1967 August 20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Clipping retrieved from notecard box.
  - Henry Luce, 1966–1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Berkeley High School, 1959–1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Thornton Wilder's records from Berkeley High School
  - The Alcestaid Opera, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Albert Boni, 1966–1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Bridge of San Luis Rey criticism, 1928–1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Cabala criticism, 1926–1927 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General criticism, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes clippings and notes on criticism of The Skin of Our Teeth.
  - A Doll's House clipping, circa 1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jed Harris, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondence between Harris and Thornton Wilder, clippings, and notes.
  - Notes on Thornton Wilder in Chicago, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Also notes on Thornton Wilder's relationship with Robert Maynard Hutchins.
  - Lawrenceville School, 1965; undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Brochures, catalogs, correspondence and notes pertaining to the Lawrenceville School where Thornton Wilder was a faculty member.
  - One Act Plays Criticism, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Harry T. Moore, 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Oberlin, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Notes, "Thornton Wilder in Oberlin- A Few Memories", and "Two Teachers"
  - Our Town materials, 1946–1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Clippings, letter from Goldstone to the editor at the New York Times, and a program from the London production of Our Town
  - The Princeton University Library Chronicle, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes an article entitled "Professor Armstrong's 'Experiment'" written by Edward Gatewood Trueblood includes reflections of Thornton Wilder.
  - Thacher School, 1965–1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Includes brochures from the Thacher, correspondence with one of Thornton Wilder's classmates, and an excerpt of Wilder's entrance evaluation.
  - The Skin of Our Teeth chapter drafts, circa 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gene Tunney, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Literary Digest clipping, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Article on Wilder's appearance in Xerxes.
  - Thew Wright, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Richard Goldstone: correspondence
    - Hutchins, Maude (photocopy), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Photocopied typescript from Maude Hutchins describing an encounter with Thornton Wilder and F. Scott Fitzgerald.
    - Wilder, Isabel (photocopies), 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Wilder, Isabel (photocopies), 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Wilder, Isabel (photocopies), 1964–1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Wilder, Isabel (photocopies), 1966–1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Wilder, Isabel (photocopies), 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Wilder, Isabel and Thornton, 1966–1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Typed and handwritten letters to and from Richard Goldstone, Isabel Wilder, and Thornton Wilder.
    - Wilder, Isabel and Thornton (photocopies), 1959–1975 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Correspondence with Isabel, Thornton, and publishers. Also includes one letter from Thacher to Amos Niven Wilder discussing Goldstone's interview with Thacher.
    - Wilder, Isabel and Thornton (photocopies), 1954–1959 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      This folder also includes correspondence between Isabel, Thornton, and the Harper and Row publishers.
    - Wilder, Isabel and Thornton (photocopies), 1961–1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Wilder, Isabel and Thornton (photocopies), 1969–1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Wilder, Thornton (photocopies and typed), 1965–1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Typescript and copies of correspondence with Thornton Wilder. Also clippings relating to Thornton Wilder.
  - Thornton Wilder clippings (photocopies), 1966–1969 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Clippings and photocopied clippings relating to Thornton Wilder and his relationship with Lady Colefax.
  - Sibyl Colefax materials, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Clippings, correspondence, and notes surrounding a New York Times article focusing on the relationship between Thornton Wilder and Sibyl Colefax.
  - Thornton Wilder biography materials, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Letter to the editor and review of Goldstone's biography in The New Haven Register
  - Thornton Wilder: correspondence
    Letters written to and from Thornton Wilder to correspondents. Most of the letters are photocopies of either handwritten or typescript letters.
    - Mrs. Barnes (photocopy), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Photocopy of a typescript letter written by Wilder to Mrs. Barnes.
    - Beer-Hofmann, Richard and Miriam (photocopies), 1935–1966 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Photocopies of letters exchanged between Thornton Wilder and Isabel Wilder and Miriam and Richard Beer-Hofman-Lens.
    - Berman, Jean Wertheimer (photocopies), 1926–1976 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Photocopies of handwritten letters by Wilder to Berman.
    - Brinton, Bradford (photocopies), 1920 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Copies of Wilder's handwritten letters to Bradford Brinton.
    - Mrs. Davis (photocopy), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Copy of handwritten letter from Wilder to Mrs. Davis.
    - General correspondence relating to Thornton Wilder's biography, 1965–1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Correspondence between Isabel Wilder and Richard Goldstone, Carol Brandy and John Macrae related to Goldstone's biography of Wilder.
    - Goldstone, Richard, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Photocopy of Wilder's handwritten letter to Richard Goldstone.
    - Greene, Waldo (photocopies), 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Photocopies of Wilder's correspondence with Greene mailed to Isabel Wilder.
    - Harper and Row, 1967–1971 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Photocopies and typescripts of correspondence between Isabel and Thornton Wilder and Cass Canfield and Beulah Hagen about Goldstone's biography.
    - Hosmer, Helen M. (photocopies), 1949–1973 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      Copies of Wilder's handwritten letters to Helen M. Hosmer.
    - Mrs. Howe (photocopy), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Photocopy of a handwritten letter from Wilder to Mrs. Howe.
    - Klemperer, Otto Latte (photocopies), 1960–1973 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      Copies of Wilder's handwritten letters to Otto Latte Klemperer.
    - Lesser, Sol (photocopies), 1940–1942 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      Photocopies of envelopes addressed from Wilder to Sol Lesser.
    - Myerberg, Michael: correspondence with Thornton Wilder and Donald Gallup (photocopies), 1940–1972 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      Copies of Wilder's correspondence and originals of Gallup's correspondence.
    - Reichenberger, Arnold: correspondence and Lope De Vega notes (photocopies), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      Photocopies of Wilder's correspondence with Reichenberger and his notes on Lope De Vega
    - Mr. Sarason (photocopies), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Copy of handwritten letter by Wilder to Mr. Sarason.
    - Schweitzer, Albert (photocopies), 1953 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      Photocopies of handwritten letters written by Wilder to Schweitzer.
    - Steward, Samuel (photocopies), 1937–1948 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      Copies of handwritten notes written by Thornton Wilder and addressed to Samuel Steward
    - Mrs. Stone (photocopies), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Photocopy of handwritten letter by Wilder to Stone.
    - Thacher School (photocopies), 1915–1917 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - The Torchbearers (photocopies), 1950 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Isabel and Thornton Wilder: letters to readers (photocopies), 1957–1960 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Copies of typescript and handwritten letters answering questions from readers.
    - Isabel and Thornton Wilder: general correspondence (photocopies), 1940–1956 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      Copies of correspondence between Thornton Wilder and Miriam Beer-Hofman- Lens, Wilder and Michael Reinhardt, and Isabel Wilder and Michael Myerberg
- 1991 Acquisition, undated; Series II; 0.21 linear feet (1 box)
  The series is arranged in chronological order as it was recieved by the library.
  The 1991 Acquisition consists of typed transcripts created by Goldstone of letters from Wilder.
  - Letters addressed to Richard Goldstone from Thornton Wilder
    - Typed transcripts from Wilder to Goldstone (7 folders), 1944–1969 (Box 4, Folder 61-67)